Guide to the Mary Elizabeth Bohannon papers, ca. 1930-1963.
Bohannon, Mary Elizabeth papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Mary Elizabeth Bohannon papers, [ca. 1930-1963]
2424
Mary Elizabeth Bohannon, 1905-1963.
5 cubic ft.
Notes, transcripts, correspondence, manuscripts, and photostats.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Notes and transcripts of 17th century English documents, diaries, account books, maps, and correspondence for her doctoral dissertation, "Studies of the Barrington Family in England During the Early Seventeenth Century," and for various later studies. There is also correspondence with Carl Becker and others concerning her research, drafts of her thesis and various articles, and photostats of the proceedings of the House of Lords for 1610 and 1614.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Historian.
Cornell University Class of 1928, Ph.D. 1932.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Notes and transcripts of 17th century English documents, diaries, account books, maps, and correspondence for her doctoral dissertation, "Studies of the Barrington Family in England During the Early Seventeenth Century," and for various later studies. There is also correspondence with Carl Becker and others concerning her research, drafts of her thesis and various articles, and photostats of the proceedings of the House of Lords for 1610 and 1614.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Bohannon, Mary Elizabeth, 1905-1963.; Barrington family.; Becker, Carl Lotus, 1873-1945.; Great Britain. Parliament. House of Lords.
Subjects:
Women--Diaries.; Historians.
Places:
England.
Form and Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Account books.; Maps.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Final draft of Ph.D. Thesis, "Studies of the Barrington Family in England During the Early Seventeenth Century." 8 folders. (Box 1)
- Outline draft and preliminary material for Life of Lady Joan Barrington. 6 folders. (Box 1)
- Miss Bohannon's thoughts about her work ("jottings") and her last notes made prior to her death, Sept. 28, 1963. 4 folders. (Box 1)
- Work in progress on the Barringtons, relating particularly to marriages, lands (purchases), debts, and elections. 5 folders. (Box 1)
- Transcripts and notes regarding Barrington MSS, some from British Museum (Egerton). 3 folders. (Box 1)
- Lady Joan Barrington's Account Book, transcripts from and notes. 5 folders. (Box 2)
- Sir Thomas Barrington's Account Books, transcripts from and notes. 7 folders. (Box 2)
- Material on Barringtons and the Puritan clergy. 6 folders. This set includes information on the baronetcy of Sir Francis, music, and gardens. (Box 2)
- Comments on material related to the Barrington work and some preliminary writing. 3 folders. (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous notes on the Barringtons. 7 folders. This set includes material on books, expenses, property, servants, and connections with New England. (Box 2)
- British Museum Egerton MSS 2650, transcripts from 3 folders. (Box 3)
- British Museum Egerton MSS 2645 and 2650, transcripts from 10 folders. (Box 3)
- British Museum Egerton MSS 2644, transcripts from 7 folders. (Box 3)
- British Museum Egerton MSS 2643, 2647, 2648, 2649, 2651, transcripts from 6 folders. (Box 3)
- British Museum Egerton MSS 2646, transcripts from 7 folders. (Box 4)
- Hatfield Broad Oak MSS, miscellaneous transcripts. 2 folders. This was the town near the Barrington Manor house. (Box 4)
- Hatfield Broad Oak MSS - Rent book 1628, Legal Expenses, "Isle of Providence" (Rhode Island & Providence Plantations, New England), Inventory of Priory 1632, Sermons, etc. - transcripts from the above. 4 folders. (Box 4)
- Preliminary MS of work on appointment to a lectureship at Hatfield. 5 folders. (Box 4)
- Notes regarding Hatfield Forest. 2 folders. (Box 4)
- Assorted oddments from Essex Lieutenancy Book. 1 folder. (Box 4)
- MSS of Trinity College, Cambridge, extracts from. 1 folder. This contains information on the Barringtons and the parsonage at Hatfield Broad Oak; also some extracts from British Museum Egerton MSS 2644. (Box 4)
- Notes from Records in Essex Record Office relating to sessions of the J.P.'s. 4 folders. (Box 4)
- British Museum MSS, extracts from additional MSS, etc.; and notes from New England Historical Register (John David Narrative). 2 folders. (Box 5)
- Manorial Rolls from British Museum, Public Record Office, Essex Record Office, and Subsidy Roll Harlow Hundred. 3 folders. (Box 5)
- Transcripts from deeds in Essex Record Office, Essex Antiquarian Society, Trinity College, Cambridge, Public Record Office (indentures), British Museum (additional charters), and Moreton's Paleography. 6 folders. (Box 5)
- Extracts from wills, etc., from British Public Records Office. 4 folders. (Box 5)
- Transcripts from Public Record Office, including Chancery Bills and Answers, Court of Wards, Inquisitions Post Mortem, Star Chamber, Certificates of Residence (Exchequer). 3 folders. (Box 5)
- State Papers, Domestic and Privy Council Records, extracts from. 4 folders. (Box 5)
- Transcripts and notes regarding Puritanism. 1 folder. (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous notes on Puritanism from printed sources. 3 folders. (Box 5)
- Preface prepared for Lords' Debates transcripts. 2 folders. (Box 6)
- Notes on House of Lords Debates. 5 folders. (Box 6)
- Copy of Lords' Debates material. 4 folders. (Box 6)
- Transcripts of Debates in House of Lords 1614 and notes relevant thereto. 8 folders. (Box 6)
- Lord Braye MS Standford Hall; transcripts of Lords' Debates, 1610, 1614. 7 folders. (Box 6)
  N.b. Various copies of the debates of 1614 can be found in #2, folders 3-5, #3, folders 1-4, #4, folders 1-4, and #5, folders 4-7.
- Altham notes and draft of article. Also an introduction. 2 folders. The Altham family was related by marriage to the Barringtons. (Box 7)
  Note: pages on yellow paper photocopied on Permalife and originals discarded. -KJ, 3/29/89
- Altham MSS, family letters. Arranged by Clive Holmes. (Box 7)
- Typescript draft, "The Essex Elections of 1604." 1 folder. (Box 7)
- Notes on History Courses. 1 folder. (Box 7)
- Correspondence, 1933-1956. 6 folders. For Carl Becker corres., see Box 8. (Box 7)
- Pamphlets on Anglo-American studies; also, Guide to Essex Record Office, 1948. (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous notes. 1 folder. (Box 7)
- Index to letters relating to the Barrington and associated families. (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous notes, some biographical and bibliographical. (Box 8)
- General notes on early 17th century. (Box 8)
- Lecture notes from her study at Cornell, some from Professors Notestein, Hebel, Becker, and Marcham. Also notes from reading preparatory to work on London before Civil War. (Box 8)
- Biographical notes on Barringtons and others. (Box 9)
- Mostly bibliographical notes with comment. (Box 9)
- Mostly relating to early 17th century Puritanism and aspects of Puritanism. (Box 9)
- Folder of 12 maps and pictures (11 photostats) of Barrington Property. (Box 9)
- 1 map, handdrawn, of Hatfield Broad Oak, removed from collection and catalogued in map collection.